Guide to the Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. papers, 1922-2007
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1923-2007; 384760; 286 boxes
  - Subseries I.E. Publication-related, 1940s-2007; 385703; 15 boxes
    Schlesinger considered himself a writer by profession, and through most of his professional life, he maintained files of correspondence related to his written work. This subseries consists of correspondence related to Schlesinger's published books, arranged alphabetically by title. The files contain a variety of correspondence, including initial solicitations of the material, negotiations, editing suggestions, input from other experts, and responses from readers both familiar and unfamiliar to Schlesinger. Schlesinger's files of letters he wrote to the editorial pages of various newspapers and magazines, as well as responses to those letters, are also included. For correspondence related to Schlesinger's published articles, see Series III.A.
    - The Age of Roosevelt, 385704 (Box 279, Folder 1-5)
    - American Presidents series, 385705 (Box 280, Folder 1-3)
    - American Presidents series, 385706 (Box 281, Folder 1-4)
    - American Statesmen series, 385707 (Box 281, Folder 5)
    - American Statesmen series, 385708 (Box 282, Folder 1)
    - The Big Decision, 385709 (Box 282, Folder 2)
    - The Bitter Heritage, 385710 (Box 282, Folder 3)
    - Collins Biographical Dictionary, 385711 (Box 282, Folder 4)
    - The Crisis of Confidence, 385712 (Box 282, Folder 5)
    - Cycles of American History, 385713 (Box 283, Folder 1-2)
    - Dictionary of American Biography, 385714 (Box 283, Folder 3)
    - The Disuniting of America, 385715 (Box 283, Folder 4-6)
    - The Disuniting of America, 385716 (Box 284, Folder 1)
    - The Dynamics of World Power, 385717 (Box 284, Folder 2)
    - Encyclopedia of the U.S. Congress, 385718 (Box 284, Folder 3)
    - Encyclopedia of U.S. Foreign Relations, 385719 (Box 284, Folder 4)
    - Facts on File, 385720 (Box 284, Folder 5)
    - The General and the President, 385721 (Box 284, Folder 6)
    - Guide to Politics, 385722 (Box 284, Folder 7)
    - History of United States Political Parties, 385723 (Box 284, Folder 8)
    - The Imperial Presidency, 385724 (Box 285, Folder 1-6)
    - A Life in the 20th Century, 385725 (Box 286, Folder 1-3)
    - The National Experience, 385726 (Box 286, Folder 4)
    - The National Experience, 385727 (Box 287, Folder 1-3)
    - Orestes Brownson, 385728 (Box 287, Folder 4-5)
    - Paths of American Thought, 385729 (Box 287, Folder 6)
    - Presidents, Parties and Power in America, 385730 (Box 287, Folder 7)
    - Robert Kennedy and His Times, 385731
      - Ballantine Books, 385732 (Box 288, Folder 1)
      - Corrections, 385733 (Box 288, Folder 2)
      - Editing, 385734 (Box 495, Folder 7)
      - English edition, 385735 (Box 288, Folder 3)
      - Esquire, 385736 (Box 288, Folder 4)
      - Foreign rights, 385737 (Box 288, Folder 5)
      - French edition, 385738 (Box 288, Folder 6)
      - John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum, 385739 (Box 495, Folder 8)
      - Letters to author, 385740 (Box 288, Folder 7)
      - Letters to Ethel Kennedy, 385741 (Box 288, Folder 8)
      - Literary Guild, 385742 (Box 288, Folder 9)
      - National Book Award, 385743 (Box 289, Folder 1)
      - Party, 385744 (Box 289, Folder 2)
      - Permission to quote, 385745 (Box 495, Folder 9-10)
      - Promotion, 385746 (Box 289, Folder 3)
      - Readers, 385747 (Box 289, Folder 4)
      - Serialization, 385748 (Box 289, Folder 5)
      - Sources, 385749 (Box 495, Folder 11)
      - TV drama, 385750 (Box 289, Folder 6)
      - General, 385751 (Box 290, Folder 1-3)
    - Running for President, 385752 (Box 291, Folder 1-4)
    - A Thousand Days, 385753 (Box 292, Folder 1-5)
    - The Vital Center, 385754 (Box 292, Folder 6-9)
    - Letters to the Editor, 385755
      - 1964-1975, 385756 (Box 406, Folder 1)
      - 1979-1994, 385757 (Box 406, Folder 2)
  - Subseries I.F. Family correspondence, 1923-2006; 385758; 7 boxes
    Whereas most correspondence, whether professional or personal, with Schlesinger's friends and colleagues was incorporated into the various filing systems represented by the other correspondence subseries, Schlesinger kept most of his family correspondence separate. Spanning childhood to old age, the family correspondence includes letters to and from Schlesinger's parents, wives and children. A greater percentage of the family correspondence is handwritten. It includes personal accounts of trips and events, as well as more introspective analyses than most of the correspondence found in the other subseries. His frequent letters to his parents during World War II provide a unique contemporary record of his thoughts and experiences at that time.
    - Kinderman, Katharine Schlesinger, 385759 (Box 293, Folder 1)
    - Schlesinger, Alexandra Emmet, 385760 (Box 293, Folder 2)
    - Schlesinger, Andrew, 385761 (Box 293, Folder 3)
    - Schlesinger, Arthur Sr., 385762 (Box 293, Folder 4)
    - Schlesinger, Christina, 385763 (Box 293, Folder 5)
    - Schlesinger, Elizabeth Bancroft, 385764 (Box 294-295)
    - Schlesinger, Elizabeth Bancroft and Arthur Sr., 385765
      - 1920s-1933, 385766 (Box 296, Folder 1-5)
      - 1938-1943, 385767 (Box 297, Folder 1-5)
      - 1944-1945, 385768 (Box 298, Folder 1-3)
      - General, 385769 (Box 298, Folder 4)
    - Schlesinger, Marian Cannon, 385770 (Box 299, Folder 1-3)
    - Schlesinger, Robert, 385771 (Box 299, Folder 4)
    - Schlesinger, Stephen, 385772 (Box 299, Folder 5)
    - Schlesinger, Tom, 385773 (Box 299, Folder 6)
    - Schlesinger children, 1960s; 385774 (Box 299, Folder 7-8)
    - Unidentified grandmother, 1930s; 385775 (Box 299, Folder 9)
- Series II: Journals, circa 1930; 1950-2003; 385776; 14 boxes
  The bulk of Schlesinger's journals cover the years 1952-2002. They document Schlesinger's work for the Democratic Party in the 1950s; his tenure as a member of John F. Kennedy's campaign and presidential staffs; his activities as a journalist, professor, and public intellectual after moving to New York in 1966; his role as an advisor to the Democratic Party and its leadership, such as Robert and Ted Kennedy, Averell Harriman, George McGovern, Bill Clinton and Al Gore; and his friendships with other politically-oriented intellectuals, the staffs of the Kennedy and other presidential administrations, and prominent cultural figures. The earliest journals in this series date back to the early 1930s and are included here in their original handwritten versions. A teenage Schlesinger began keeping them to record his travel experiences and his observations and musings about his destinations.
  Schlesinger wrote not just for public consumption, but also for himself, and his personal journals provide perhaps the greatest insight into his opinions, and in some cases his daily life. Although entries include some information and reflections on Schlesinger's private life, their focus, like Schlesinger's, is on current events. The journals are not deeply introspective. Personal remarks usually center on his progress on current writing, his teaching, and personal and family milestones. Mentions of such topics are, in any case, brief.
  Most of the journal entries report and comment on the news of the day. Schlesinger is often present and frequently participating in the events he describes. For instance, Schlesinger went to nearly every Democratic National Convention during his adulthood, and often had some official or unofficial role or influence; he was on President Kennedy's staff and participated in meetings on such topics as Cuba, Vietnam, and civil rights legislation; he drafted speeches, and took official trips, such as one to South America in 1961; and he found himself at the center of the events in the aftermath of the President's assassination. Later, after leaving official public life, his friends and colleagues in political and other circles continued to call on Schlesinger for advice and to comment on their plans of action, speeches, letters, and editorials. At dinners, cocktail parties, and informal gatherings, he was there as Robert Kennedy decided whether to run against Lyndon Johnson in 1968, as George McGovern mounted his 1972 campaign, and as Ted Kennedy struggled seemingly every four years over his presidential aspirations. His views on Bill Clinton's campaign and presidency are here, as well as his contributions as an unofficial consultant to the Al Gore campaign in 2000.
  Schlesinger was very active socially and many of his entries are framed as reports on a party, a trip to a friend's country home, or a lunch at the Century Club. Although he is often not the main character in the events about which he writes, he narrates with a distinct point of view while reporting facts and the opinions of others.
  In addition to the usual motivations for keeping a journal, Schlesinger used his as an aid in writing his books, letters, articles, memorials, and speeches recalling past events. For this reason, entries may contain annotations made some years after the fact. Schlesinger also sent copies of pages to colleagues to help them recall or write about specific past events. Although an edited version of these journals was published after Schlesinger's death (xxJournals, 1952-2000xx by Arthur M. Schlesinger; edited by Andrew Schlesinger and Stephen Schlesinger. New York: Penguin Press, 2007), it is not clear whether or not he planned for their publication in some form as he wrote them. He certainly used them as source material for his memoirs, however, as well as for other writings requiring him to look retrospectively at events in his own lifetime.
  The journal entries are sometimes supplemented with copies of letters, memoranda, speeches, invitations, meeting minutes, and other related material. Of note, in this regard, are the letters to and from John Kennedy during the 1960 campaign. Some earlier entries, in the 1950s, consist of actual meeting minutes and notes rather than conscious journal entries.
  The journals are typed, though there are some handwritten annotations and additions. Several entries appear to have been typed from notes (by Schlesinger or his secretary, Gretchen Stewart); others were written directly on the typewriter. It is not possible to determine when or who typed the entries, except when Schlesinger refers explicitly to the action of typing himself. (See, for instance, January 26, 1974 when his son Robert comes in and taps on a few keys in mid-sentence.) During the 1950s, a variety of paper and typewriters were used. Sometimes copies were made of pages or pages were retyped later from carbons or copies. Multiple copies of the same entries have been retained when there appears to be some possible variation.
  Entries in the journal are dated the day Schlesinger wrote them rather than with the date of the events described. Depending on the regularity with which he was keeping the journal at the time, entries could cover a single day or take a more retrospective view of a preceding month or even months.
  The years of Adlai Stevenson's unsuccessful campaigns for president, 1952 especially, are well represented; otherwise entries are sporadic in the 1950s. Schlesinger began keeping his journal more regularly during Kennedy's presidential campaign. It is only in 1961 that the journal takes on regularity and uniformity in presentation, and he begins to use continuous page numbers. Schlesinger's White House years, 1961-1963, are the best documented in the journals, averaging over 400 pages per year. The journals for most other years consist of 60-100 pages, the exceptions being 1968, 1971, 1976, 1979, 1980, 1982, and 1983 which are each 150 pages or longer. Schlesinger tended to write in his journal more often during important political years, notably those with presidential elections.
  - 1930s, 385777; 10 items (Box 309, Volume 1-10)
  - 1950; 1952, 385778 (Box 310, Folder 1-12)
  - 1953-1961, 385779 (Box 311, Folder 1-18)
  - 1962-1963 June, 385780 (Box 312, Folder 1-17)
  - 1963 July-1968 June, 385781 (Box 313, Folder 1-26)
  - 1968 July-1972, 385782 (Box 314, Folder 1-27)
  - 1973-1978, 385783 (Box 315, Folder 1-34)
  - 1979-1983, 385784 (Box 316, Folder 1-39)
  - 1984-1987, 385785 (Box 317, Folder 1-26)
  - 1988-1992, 385786 (Box 318, Folder 1-37)
  - 1993-1997 Aug, 385787 (Box 319, Folder 1-39)
  - 1997 Oct-2003, 385788 (Box 320, Folder 1-20)
  - Drafts, 385789
    - 1961-1974, 385790 (Box 321, Folder 1-5)
    - 1974-1987, 385791 (Box 322, Folder 1-3)
- Series III: Writings, 1946-2005; 385792; 64 boxes
  This series includes Schlesinger's unpublished work or early drafts of published material. Additional drafts, many of articles written for academic and popular periodicals, can be found attached to correspondence in Series I.E.
  - Subseries III. A. Articles, 1948-1994, 2005; 385793; 23 boxes
    - 1948-1958, 385794 (Box 256, Folder 1-30)
    - 1959-1966, 385795 (Box 257, Folder 1-33)
    - 1967-1968, 385796 (Box 258, Folder 1-35)
    - 1969, 385797 (Box 259, Folder 1-19)
    - 1970, 385798 (Box 260, Folder 1-22)
    - 1971, 385799 (Box 261, Folder 1-22)
    - 1972, 385800 (Box 262, Folder 1-23)
    - 1973, 385801 (Box 263, Folder 1-31)
    - 1974, 385802 (Box 264, Folder 1-31)
    - 1975, 385803 (Box 265, Folder 1-24)
    - 1976, 385804 (Box 266, Folder 1-17)
    - 1977-1978, 385805 (Box 267, Folder 1-29)
    - 1979, 385806 (Box 268, Folder 1-34)
    - 1980-1981, 385807 (Box 269, Folder 1-46)
    - 1982, 385808 (Box 270, Folder 1-24)
    - 1983, 385809 (Box 271, Folder 1-22)
    - 1984-1985, 385810 (Box 272, Folder 1-37)
    - 1986, 385811 (Box 273, Folder 1-17)
    - 1987-1988, 385812 (Box 274, Folder 1-34)
    - 1989, 385813 (Box 275, Folder 1-21)
    - 1990-1991, 385814 (Box 276, Folder 1-21)
    - 1991-1992, 385815 (Box 277, Folder 1-25)
    - 1993-1994; 2005, 385816 (Box 278, Folder 1-32)
  - Subseries III. B. Lectures, 1946-2003; 385817; 31 boxes
    Schlesinger was both a professor and highly sought-after speaker. This subseries includes his lecture notes for some of his classes at the City University of New York, as well as individual lectures and lecture series he gave for various groups around the world. Schlesinger lectured in venues all around the United States, including numerous university commencements. International settings for the lectures include England, Italy, Germany, the Netherlands, Japan and Korea. This subseries also incorporates Schlesinger's testimony before various Congressional subcommittees. In many cases, the typewritten lecture notes contain handwritten annotations by Schlesinger and supporting material, such as correspondence with the sponsors of the lecture.
    Schlesinger was called upon to share his insights on both American history and current events. Many of the lectures in the collection reflect his expertise in the life and presidency of Franklin Roosevelt, including a series of lectures on Roosevelt and his times for the London Commonwealth Fund. The life and legacy of John F. Kennedy was another frequent subject from the 1960s onward. The notes for his year-long class entitled Intellectual History extend beyond American history to all of Western philosophy. His series of lectures on xxVenice and the American Novelxx combine his interests in history and art. When American politics dominated the news, Schlesinger contributed to the discussion in his personal appearances. Lectures from the mid-1970s include xxImpeachment: Paradox & Dilemmaxx and xxWhat Do We Tell Our Students?-Thoughts After Watergatexx. The subseries also contains notable speeches from such special occasions as Adlai Stevenson's memorial service and the seventy-fifth anniversary of the New York Public Library.
    Although not listed in this guide, the collection contains sound and video recordings of various Schlesinger appearances and interviews. They include the four-part CBS News series "Schlesinger in Albany," interviews publicizing Robert Kennedy and His Times, and appearances with John Kenneth Galbraith, Larry King, and other notable figures. Sound and video recordings are unavailable for use at this time pending preservation transfer.
    - 1946-1957, 385818 (Box 323, Folder 1-9)
    - 1957-1960, 385819 (Box 324, Folder 1-5)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Commonwealth Fund, London), 1959; 385820 (Box 325, Folder 1-3)
    - Intellectual History, 1959-1960; 385821 (Box 326, Folder 1-5)
    - 1960-1964, 385822 (Box 327, Folder 1-23)
    - 1964-1966, 385823 (Box 328, Folder 1-21)
    - 1966, 385824 (Box 329, Folder 1-7)
    - 1966-1967, 385825 (Box 330, Folder 1-13)
    - 1967-1968, 385826 (Box 331, Folder 1-14)
    - 1968, 385827 (Box 332, Folder 1-9)
    - 1968-1969, 385828 (Box 333, Folder 1-17)
    - 1970-1971, 385829 (Box 334, Folder 1-13)
    - 1971-1972, 385830 (Box 335, Folder 1-9)
    - 1972-1973, 385831 (Box 336, Folder 1-12)
    - 1973-1974, 385832 (Box 337, Folder 1-15)
    - 1974, 385833 (Box 338, Folder 1-9)
    - 1975-1976, 385834 (Box 339, Folder 1-14)
    - 1976-1978, 385835 (Box 340, Folder 1-7)
    - 1978-1979, 385836 (Box 341, Folder 1-16)
    - 1980s, 385837 (Box 342, Folder 1-2)
    - 1980-1981, 385838 (Box 342, Folder 3-12)
    - 1981-1982, 385839 (Box 343, Folder 1-15)
    - 1982-1983, 385840 (Box 344, Folder 1-13)
    - 1984, 385841 (Box 345, Folder 1-10)
    - 1985-1986, 385842 (Box 346, Folder 1-10)
    - 1986-1987, 385843 (Box 347, Folder 1-7)
    - 1987-1988, 385844 (Box 348, Folder 1-10)
    - 1988-1989, 385845 (Box 349, Folder 1-15)
    - 1990-1991, 385846 (Box 350, Folder 1-18)
    - 1991-1992, 385847 (Box 351, Folder 1-18)
    - 1992-1993, 385848 (Box 352, Folder 1-18)
    - 1994-2003, 385849 (Box 353, Folder 1-11)
  - Subseries III. C. Robert Kennedy and His Times, 1970s; 385850; 7 boxes
    xxRobert Kennedy and His Timesxx is one of Schlesinger's most significant and best-remembered books. A painstakingly researched historical biography, it told the story of the late Robert Kennedy in the context of the era in which he rose to prominence. Although Schlesinger was a close friend of Kennedy, and includes personal reminiscences in the book, xxRobert Kennedy and His Timesxx is not a memoir or a personal history (as was, for example, xxA Thousand Daysxx). The two early drafts of the book included in this subseries illustrate the writing and editing process a Schlesinger history book would undergo before publication.
    - Draft 1, 385851
      - Foreword; Chapters 1-12, 385852 (Box 354, Folder 1-12)
      - Chapters 13-22, 385853 (Box 355, Folder 1-10)
      - Chapters 23-36, 385854 (Box 356, Folder 1-13)
      - Chapters 37-48, 385855 (Box 357, Folder 1-12)
    - Draft 2, 385856
      - Foreword; Chapters 1-14, 385857 (Box 358, Folder 1-14)
      - Chapters 15-27, 385858 (Box 359, Folder 1-13)
      - Chapters 28-41, 385859 (Box 360, Folder 1-14)
  - Subseries III. D. Additional Writings, 1948-2005; 385860; 3 boxes
    In addition to being in demand as an academic and popular lecturer, Schlesinger's oratorical skills made him a frequent commencement speaker and eulogist. This subseries includes Schlesinger's own typed copies of various commencement addresses, arranged chronologically, as well as memorial tributes to many of his friends and colleagues, arranged alphabetically. One unique item in this subseries is a dramatic adaptation of Henry Adams's xxDemocracyxx, one of Schlesinger's favorite written works, although it is uncertain what, if any, venue was planned for performing the adaptation.
    - Commencement addresses, 1978-2001; 385861 (Box 361, Folder 1-3)
    - Democracy (adaptation of Henry Adams book), 385862 (Box 361, Folder 4)
    - Memorial tributes, 1948-2005; 385863
      - A-L, 385864 (Box 362, Folder 1-5)
      - M-Y; unidentified, 385865 (Box 363, Folder 1-4)
- Series IV: Research Files, 385866; 142 boxes
  Some of Schlesinger's research files consisted of material gathered on subjects in which he took an interest, or which might have provided the basis for a book, article, or lecture, while his other research files were directly connected to the history books he wrote. The files contain published material, transcripts, notes, and annotations.
  - Subseries IV. A. Subject Files, 1950s-2000s; 385867; 73 boxes
    Schlesinger kept current on a wide variety of subjects, including political, cultural and intellectual topics. Even as he researched and wrote his books, he was often called upon to write articles, lecture, and appear on panels, and he consequently maintained files on those subjects which interested him or had the potential to contribute ideas for one of his articles or lectures. His subject files contained clippings, notes, student papers, letters to and from Schlesinger himself, relevant third-party correspondence, and interview transcripts. This subseries offers a glimpse of how Schlesinger gathered data on subjects of interest, and how that data may have influenced his thinking.
    Some of the more extensive files Schlesinger maintained included those on international affairs, such as the Communist Party, the Cold War, Vietnam, and the Bay of Pigs. Schlesinger's interest in American governmental affairs manifested itself in files on McCarthyism, the presidency, the vice presidency (which Schlesinger believed should be abolished), and various presidential campaigns.
    Having continued his father's practice of polling historians for their rankings of the relative success of American presidents, Schlesinger kept records on both his polls and his father's, tracing the changes over time in how some presidents were viewed by American historians. His file on his own book xxThe Cycles of American Historyxx provides support for his theory, also adapted from his father's, that the American electorate alternated between periods of liberalism and conservatism on a thirty-year cycle.
    In some cases, Schlesinger's subject files centered on individuals or organizations of both historical and personal significance. John Kennedy, Robert Kennedy, Reinhold Niebuhr, Adlai Stevenson, Averell Harriman and even Schlesinger himself have files dedicated to them, as do Harvard University and Americans for Democratic Action.
    Of special note are the subject files on multiculturalism, National History Standards, and Schlesinger's book xxThe Disuniting of Americaxx. When Schlesinger was on the committee for establishing a set of history standards for American education, he publicly disavowed the results because of his differences with the rest of the committee over its application of multicultural principles. While not objecting to more inclusive curricula, Schlesinger believed that the new standards risked turning history into "therapy." His reaction became enormously controversial, and the ensuing response to his statements led him to write xxThe Disuniting of Americaxx, a treatise outlining what he saw as the shift from a shared American culture to a splintered one. These subject files provide insight into Schlesinger's thoughts on the matter, as well as the response to his public statements on the issue.
    - Academe, 385868 (Box 364, Folder 1)
    - Academy of American Poets, 385869 (Box 364, Folder 2)
    - Adams, Brooks, 385870 (Box 364, Folder 3)
    - Adams, Henry, 385871 (Box 365, Folder 1)
    - Africa, 385872 (Box 365, Folder 2)
    - Africa Conference, 385873 (Box 365, Folder 3)
    - Age of Action, 385874 (Box 365, Folder 4)
    - Age of Jackson, 385875 (Box 365, Folder 5-6)
    - Age of Jackson, 385876 (Box 366, Folder 1-2)
    - Age of Roosevelt, 385877 (Box 366, Folder 3)
    - Alarums, 385878 (Box 366, Folder 4)
    - Alliance for Progress, 385879 (Box 366, Folder 5)
    - America, meaning of, 385880 (Box 367, Folder 1)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 385881